let A and D be fixed real numbers in N
be a non-negative integer then consider
the sum a plus a plus d plus a plus 2
times D and so on up to a plus n times D
we can represent this sum of an
arithmetic sequence using a staircase
diagram consisting of a bunch of
rectangles the first level has a
rectangle with area a the next one has
two rectangles in closing area a plus d
and so on up to the last level which has
an area in closing a plus n times D but
then imagine a second staircase diagram
rotated and fit together with the
original to form a rectangle as shown
here this rectangle has a length given
by 2 times a plus n times d and a width
given by n plus one so the area enclosed
in this rectangle is n plus 1 times 2A
plus n times D and that must be equal to
2 times the original arithmetic sum this
means that the sum where I ranges from 0
to n of a plus I D must be n plus 1
times 2A plus ND all divided by 2.